<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The magistrates authority asserted, in a sermon, preached at the cathedral in Norwich by James Paston ...</title>
            <author>Paston, James, d. 1722?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56562</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P666</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13819</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12033716</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12033716</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52836</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56562)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52836)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 573:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The magistrates authority asserted, in a sermon, preached at the cathedral in Norwich by James Paston ...</title>
                  <author>Paston, James, d. 1722?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 25 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. and are to be sold by Richard Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52836:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52836:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Magiſtrates Authority ASSERTED In A SERMON, Preached at the <hi>Cathedral</hi> in NORWICH.</p>
            <p>By JAMES PASTON, M.A. <hi>Rector of</hi> Tinningham <hi>in</hi> Suffolk.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Pet. 2.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Submit your ſelves to every Ordnance of man for the Lords ſake.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Chiſwell,</hi> at the Roſe and Crown in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52836:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52836:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful Robert Bendiſh <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Mayor of the City of <hi>NORWICH.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NOthing but your Importunity could have been ſufficiently prevalent to make this Diſcourſe appear in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick: for I am ſo conſcious of my own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abilities, that I ſhould have thought your Candour and Zeal for the good of the Church and Nation had impoſed too much upon your Judgment, when you moved me to let you print it; but that all men give ſo full <hi>Encomiums</hi> of your worth, that I muſt have no ſmall ſtock of Infidelity to doubt it. Such as it is, I here humbly preſent you with, and deſire it may have its deſigned end; that it may promote <hi>Unity</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> and perſwade men not to put that aſunder in Practice, which God hath joyned in Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept,
<pb facs="tcp:52836:3"/> namely <hi>Fear</hi> to <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> to his <hi>Vice-gerents;</hi> into the number of which your Merits have worthily promoted you, and made you <hi>Repreſentative</hi> in that great and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble City, unto him who is <hi>Repreſentative</hi> to the great King of Heaven. And therefore although the World may blame my Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in this Action, yet it cannot ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe my Obedience, ſince it is to your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; and eſpecially ſince thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands deſcended ſo low as to become Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, and thereby rendred themſelves the more obliging: which ſince they have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me the boldneſs to venture theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pages abroad, I beg that of you, which your native Generoſity will prompt you to vouchſafe, namely your Patronage of them, and hereby you will honour</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant in Chriſt <hi>JAMES PASTON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:52836:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Beg no more at your hands, than commmon Charity will oblige you to grant, namely to believe me (who never gave you cauſe to do otherwiſe) in telling you that this following Diſcourſe had not been committed to the Preſs, but upon the importunity of the Right Worſhipful the Mayor of <hi>Norwich,</hi> and ſome other Friends, whoſe Judgment I have cauſe to eſteem above mine own. If you will accuſe me for my Conceſſion: (although unwillingly obtained) I confeſs I have only this to plead in my excuſe; that my intentions were honeſt. I am ready alſo to concur with any Man, whoſe opinion it is, that the Subject might have been much better handled, by ſome more able and judicious Advocate; and for this reaſon have I been ſo long ſtrugling (ſince I preached it) againſt the Arguments uſed by my Friends, before I would yeild, being very loth to appear in publick ſo early. Therefore, as I hope you will not doubt of my veracity, ſo neither will I queſtion your good-nature, till I have juſt cauſe; but will believe you will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don a fault committed with ſo much reluctancy. As for the Diſcourſe it ſelf, the Compoſure of it is too mean for any mans envy, and the deſign of it too good for any Mans ſcorn, and therefore I promiſe my ſelf-ſecurity.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:52836:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52836:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. XIII. V.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Wherefore ye muſt needs be ſubject, not only for wrath, but alſo for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>RDER is a thing ſo neceſſary to the preſervation of the Univerſe, that ſhould this be diſſolved, all things would ſoon relapſe, and degenerate into that Chaos out of which the great Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator at firſt raiſed them. The Earth was without form, and void, and darkneſs was upon the face of the deep; and confuſion, like a cloud over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread and concealed the greateſt glories, till the God of Order divided things from things, and ranked every being into its fitting place; giving to the Sun, Moon and Stars their proper ſpheres; the Earth that ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation from whence it ſhall never be moved; and ſetting bars and bounds to the fluctuations of the Sea, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing limits to its boiſterous and inſulting waves, and then did the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpeak the Wiſdom and Glory of its Maker.</p>
            <p>And as the moſt wiſe Creator ſaw this neceſſary in the greater World, ſo likewiſe in the <hi>Microcoſm,</hi> Man,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52836:5"/> the Epitome thereof. Ordering therefore a <hi>Superiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>Inferiority</hi> between the Soul and the Body; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the one capable of ruling, the other of being ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; nay, giving to every member its due place and office, and uniting them by that need they have of each others help and ſupport.</p>
            <p>And accordingly has Nature taught the moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Nations to order their Bodies Politick: and in the Sacred Writ, we no ſooner read of Man, but we read of Dominion and Subjection: nay, the grand Council of Heaven had them in deſign together: for at the ſame time that God ſaid, <hi>Let us make Man in our Image, and after our likeneſs,</hi> he alſo ſaid, <hi>and let him have Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> and therefore, ſo ſoon as that Bleſſing (Increaſe and Multiply) began to be effectual, every man was King and Prieſt in his own Family, and many Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies combined into Nations, and were ordered into ranks and degrees.</p>
            <p>And this was taught not onely by the Documents of Nature, but alſo by the God of Nature himſelf: who when he choſe a peculiar People, he inſtituted a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of King and Prieſt, and led them by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> A King to rule, and a Prieſt whoſe lips ſhould preſerve knowledge: his divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom knowing that all could not be equal, but that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man muſt keep that order, and obſerve that ſtation, wherein Providence has placed him: <hi>Wherefore ye muſt needs be ſubject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor did <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> lay level the goodly Symetry of this glorious Fabrick, or reduce the beauty of Order into the ruinous heap of its priſtine Confuſion: and therefore the Apoſtle uſes the ſame kind of Arguing, to perſwade us to Subjection and Obedience in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52836:5"/> going Chap. <hi>v.</hi> 4. and ſo on, telling us, that as we have many members in one Body, and all members have not the ſame Office; ſo we being many, are one body in <hi>Chriſt:</hi> but yet not equal, but every one members one of another. Having then (ſaid he) gifts differing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Grace that is given us, whether Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, let us propheſy according to the proportion of Faith; or Miniſtry, let us wait on our miniſtring; or, he that teacheth on teaching: or he that exhorteth, on exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: he that giveth, let him do it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>with liberality:</hi> he that ruleth, with diligence. By theſe and ſome other Duties which he preſſeth in the following verſes, he ſufficiently intimates that we ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to live peaceably with all men, by keeping every one in his due order; this is the way and means to it. <hi>Wherefore ye muſt needs be ſubject, not onely for wrath but alſo for Conſcience ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words of the Apoſtle are a Concluſion, and inference from what had been premiſed in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going part of the Chapter; in the beginning whereof he layes down this injunction, <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher Powers,</hi> and he gives a ſufficient Reaſon why Subjection muſt be yielded to ſuch: <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>there is no power but of God;</hi> whether it be that power which Chriſt has left in his Church, or that of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Emperours under whom ye live; The Powers that be, are ordained of God. The Sin of reſiſting therefore is not ſmall; <hi>For whoſoever reſiſteth the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> though he may deceive himſelf, and think he only reſiſteth man, yet his reſiſtance reaches further: <hi>He reſiſteth the ordinance of God:</hi> this is the nature of the ſin, and therefore, <hi>He that doth reſiſt, ſhall receive to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Damnation;</hi> this is the puniſhment. For further,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52836:6"/> (as he tells them, <hi>verſe</hi> 3.) The end and deſign of Gods ſetling Rulers over them, is not to terrifie them from good, but from evil; and therefore they ought to be afraid to reſiſt that power, which is given of God for ſo good an end: which, ſince it is ſo good, they muſt needs <hi>be ſubject,</hi> not only for <hi>wrath,</hi> not only for fear of the ſword which the Magiſtrate bears; but although he ſhould lay by his ſword, though he ſhould ſuſpend his puniſhment, yet merely <hi>For Conſcience ſake they muſt be ſubject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this is plaint to common ſenſe, that the Apoſtle injoynes ſubjection, not only in civil, but alſo in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual concerns: but in what particulars this Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to be yielded, he hath not declared either here or in any other place. The Church of the Jews was ſtrictly limited and preſcribed in many particular cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and whoſoever ſhould dare to trangreſs theſe, or make any alteration in theſe punctilio's, was ſure to run inevitably upon a Curſe. But Chriſt has given us an enlargement, and has granted liberty to the Chriſtian Church, to inſtitute and appoint what indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Ceremonies ſhould be uſed: and therefore we finde onely general Rules laid down, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.16. the Apoſtle ſpeaking concerning <hi>Timotheus</hi> and <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los,</hi> fellow-workers together with him in the Lord; <hi>I beſeech you brethren</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſubmit your ſelves unto ſuch, and to every one that helpeth with us, and laboureth.</hi> And ſo again, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.17. <hi>Obey thoſe that have the rule over you, for they watch for your ſouls, as they that muſt give an account:</hi> and the Apoſtle St. Peter, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lord's ſake, whether it be to the King as ſupream, or unto Governours that are ſent by him, for the puniſhment of evil
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52836:6"/> doers, and the praiſe of them that do well.</hi> And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle St Paul, writing to <hi>Titus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Crete,</hi> tells him, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. that <hi>For this cauſe he left him</hi> there, that he might <hi>ſet things in order that were wanting:</hi> ſo that to make our Chriſtian freedome, a ground of Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, is to uſe our liberty <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as a cover or <hi>cloke for our maliciouſneſs.</hi> For obedience to Governours both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, is as plainly commanded in the writings of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as love to God and our Neighbour: and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience is ſo evidently forbidden, that unleſs we be blinded either with Pride or Ignorance, we may as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſcern the prohibition, as <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> and <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, not onely the Goſpel, but Nature it ſelf has writ it in ſuch Characters, and ſo univerſally legible, that all Nations have read and obeyed it: and no peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple though never ſo barbarous, were ſcarce ever yet found, that had not a Government in Spiritual and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil concerns. So that Subjection and Government have been <hi>ſemper &amp; ubique,</hi> at all times and in all places. So that he that diſputes againſt Authority, at the ſame time argues againſt the Sacred Scripture, and Reaſon, and the practice of all Ages and Nations. For Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, we ſee, is commanded to be yielded to Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, whether in Church or State, to Eccleſiaſtical or Civil Power, or if it be both united in one; but in what particulars is not here ſpecified; therefore ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the method of the Text, we will enquire,
<list>
                  <item>I. In what things we muſt be ſubject.</item>
                  <item>II. Wherein lies the neceſſity of ſuch Subjection.</item>
                  <item>III. The Reaſons laid down by the Apoſtle.
<list>
                        <item>1. For <hi>Wrath.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. For <hi>Conſcience ſake.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:52836:7"/>I. In what things we muſt be ſubject to the higher Powers: and that is, Firſt, In all things God has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded. Secondly, In all things which he has not plainly and evidently forbidden: and that not only in Civil, but alſo in Spiritual matters: and for proof of this laſt, I chiefly deſign my following Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="1">I. In all things God has commanded, we muſt be ſubject to our Superiours: and to uſe Arguments to prove this, would be needleſs and ſuperfluous: for I ſuppoſe if our Superiours commanded Love, and Peace and Unity, we ought to obey, becauſe God and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have commanded the ſame things; but in regard that every thing is not ſet down, nor every particular circumſtance ſpecified which may ſerve in order to the preſervation of them, Therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">II. If our Superiours preſcribe this or that way for the attaining to, and preſervation of them; if this or that way be not forbidden by God, we muſt in this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be ſubject. For although it be true that Chriſt has made us free, yet nevertheleſs St. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts us, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. even for <hi>His ſake, to ſubmit to every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man:</hi> and not to <hi>uſe this liberty as a cloke of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſneſs,</hi> as a pretence for Rebellion and Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for that freedom which Chriſt purchaſed for us, is, Freedom from ſin, Freedom from the curſe of the Law; Freedom from the Ceremonial Law, from Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion and Sacrifices: and it is certain, that when <hi>Chriſt</hi> abrogated thoſe Circumſtances which belonged to the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> he did not inſtitute others as appenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to the <hi>Chriſtian Worſhip:</hi> but yet he gave power to thoſe whom he left in his ſtead to do it. If he had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted any himſelf, they had been indiſpenſably ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary whether our Superiours had commanded them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52836:7"/> or not: But now they are not ſo <hi>indiſpenſably</hi> neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, till ſuch time, and no longer than the Commands of our lawful Superiours make them ſo.</p>
            <p>For not the leaſt drop of <hi>Chriſt's</hi> blood was ſo vainly ſpent as to purchaſe freedom for us in things abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indifferent, that is, in ſuch things as were in their own nature indifferent, concerning which there was no command: For theſe were free before, and therefore free to be performed before and after they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and the Command is neceſſarily to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed.</p>
            <p>It is true, if the Supreme King of Heaven <hi>evidently forbids</hi> what his <hi>Subſtitutes</hi> upon Earth <hi>injoyn;</hi> we know which to obey, <hi>God</hi> rather than <hi>Man.</hi> But if it be not <hi>evidently</hi> forbidden, nay if it be <hi>doubtful,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God has forbidden or not, we are bound to obey, at leaſt till we ſee ſome <hi>manifeſt</hi> and very <hi>plauſible</hi> ground for our heſitation. For herein we carry along with us the virtue of obedience, and God's Precept by his Apoſtle <hi>(Submit your ſelves)</hi> will be our plea; whereas if we err the other way, there is ſcarce any thing will render our delinqency excuſable.</p>
            <p>And therefore if we examine the ſufferings of Saints and Martyrs, we ſhall ſcarce find that any (who were truly called ſo) ever ſuffered for diſobedience in things <hi>indifferent;</hi> and made neceſſary by lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. <hi>Shadrach, Meſech,</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> Dan. 3. were thrown into the fiery furnace, rather than they would obey the Kings command: But the Command was not in a thing <hi>indifferent,</hi> but <hi>quite contrary to the Command of God,</hi> namely to worſhip an Image, <hi>Daniel,</hi> Ch. 6. was thrown into the Lions Den, not becauſe of ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or kneeling in his Devotions, but meerly becauſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52836:8"/> he prayed unto God. And the Woman and her ſeven ſons, 2 <hi>Macc.</hi> 7. embraced Death rather than they would eat Swines fleſh: But this God had <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbidden,</hi> and had not left it <hi>indifferent.</hi> Saint <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> was beheaded for reproving <hi>Herods</hi> inceſt, St. <hi>Stephen</hi> for reproving the Jews infidelity. And the Apoſtles underwent Bonds, and Impriſonments, and Death, rather than they would forbear preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt to the unbelieving Jews and Heathens; for he had immediately commanded them ſo to do. And that <hi>Theban</hi> Legion under <hi>Mauritius,</hi> conſiſting of 6666 <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſuffered death in the days of <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> not for diſobedience in an <hi>indifferent thing,</hi> but for refuſing to <hi>offer Sacrifice to the Heathen Gods:</hi> None of theſe ſuffered for diſobedience in <hi>things indifferent.</hi> Nor do we read of any that refuſed obedience to thoſe indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent things which the Apoſtles injoyned; as to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from things ſtrangled, and from blood, which after Chriſt aboliſhed the Ceremonial Law became abſolutely of an indifferent nature; but did any cry out of intrenchment of their Chriſtian Liberty for this?</p>
            <p>We have therefore neither Precept nor Example for diſobedience in ſuch things. The Scripture in general commands <hi>obedience to God and Man,</hi> and he has expreſt greater diſpleaſure to thoſe who have diſobeyed his <hi>Subſtitutes,</hi> than to thoſe who have more immediately rebelled againſt <hi>himſelf:</hi> And therefore we never read that the Earth opened her mouth and ſwallowed up any, but ſuch as would <hi>not be ſubject to Earthly Superiours.</hi> A cup of cold water given to Chriſt's Diſciples, he takes as given to himſelf, and the reward ſhall be accordingly; and ſo diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52836:8"/> to his <hi>Subſtitutes,</hi> he takes as to himſelf. For,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 10.6.</note> 
               <hi>He that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me:</hi> Luke 10.10. and he that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> obeyeth his Superiors, at the ſame time pays his homage to Chriſt, and this is the Sphere of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and our Obedience, namely things <hi>indifferent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is no new thing; for notwithſtanding the Church of the Jews had the peculiar Circumſtances of God's worſhip ſo preciſely appointed them; yet we find that their Governours did introduce ſome things of an indifferent nature; and therefore we read, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.1 that <hi>David</hi> and the Captains of the Hoſt ſeparated to the ſervice of the ſons of <hi>Aſaph,</hi> and the reſt, who ſhould Propheſie with Harps, and with Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, and Cymbals, which things were never appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Law. They alſo inſtituted Feaſts and Faſts, as the Feaſt of <hi>Dedication,</hi> and the Feaſt of <hi>Purim,</hi> which were ſo far from being blamed by our Saviour, that he graced the firſt of them with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, as we read <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.22. And the <hi>third,</hi> and <hi>ſixth,</hi> and <hi>ninth</hi> hours of Prayer had no <hi>Injunction</hi> to inforce them but Cuſtom, or at moſt a Law of the Jews <hi>own</hi> making; and yet were obſerved by the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as we may read in theſe ſeveral places of the <hi>Acts ch.</hi> 2.15.—3.1.—10.9. nor were any of the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of the Jews reprehended by our Saviour, but ſuch as were contrary to the Law of God delivered in his Word, or by the <hi>Dictates of Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor will it at all excuſe our diſobedience, if we plead that we ſee no reaſon why ſuch and ſuch things ſhould be enjoyned: Eor as the virtues of <hi>Humility, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Meekneſs</hi> are expreſt in our obedience to ſuch things: So, much <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Uncharitableneſs</hi> is betray'd by our diſobedience; for the humble man will conſider,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52836:9"/> that although he <hi>himſelf</hi> ſees no neceſſity, why ſuch things ſhould be commanded, yet that his <hi>Superiours</hi> may, to whom God and Nature has made him a <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> and therefore he ſubmits. But the proud and ſelf-conceited perſon ſcorns to be impoſed upon, thinks himſelf at leaſt as wiſe, if not wiſer than his Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and is ready to cry out with <hi>Corah</hi> to the <hi>Rulers</hi> of the people,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.3.</note> 
               <hi>Ye take too much upon you:</hi> Whereas if we ſee no <hi>abſolute neceſſity</hi> of our diſobedience, we muſt needs <hi>be ſubject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if obedience is to be yielded to no injunction but ſuch as we can ſee a reaſon for, <hi>God himſelf</hi> would have been <hi>diſobeyed</hi> upon this ſcore, for he himſelf has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded ſuch things as no <hi>natural neceſſity</hi> appears to be the Parent: For what piece of excellency, or what <hi>natural neceſſity</hi> was there for <hi>Abraham's</hi> ſlaying his innocent ſon, who was Heir of the Promiſe? yet this God commanded, and this he would have done, had not a counter command ſtayed his Sacrificing-knife: And ſo what natural <hi>intrinſick neceſſity</hi> was there of the cutting off a Child's fore-skin, or of waſhing the hands and garments in order to purification from ſin? yet theſe things God commanded; and although there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared no manifeſt neceſſity of the Command, yet ſo neceſſary was obedience, that it was performed to them: and as God, ſo likwiſe his ſervants, even under the Goſpel have laid upon Men Commands of this nature; as the Apoſtles enjoyned abſtinence from <hi>things ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and from blood.</hi> Such Commands as theſe have been given by the Supream King of Heaven, and by thoſe whom he has appointed Rulers upon Earth, and were obeyed, and the obedience was crowned with rewards, and the diſobedience puniſhed with revenge.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52836:9"/> 
               <hi>Subjection</hi> therefore may be <hi>neceſſary,</hi> when for ought we know the <hi>Command is not,</hi> and the obedience ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and acceptable.</p>
            <p>And where has the great God of Heaven and Earth forbidden the <hi>Dij minorum gentium?</hi> where has he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited thoſe of whom he ſaid, <hi>they are Gods,</hi> to inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute ſuch Ceremonies, and appoint ſuch Orders as they ſhall think are decent? or where has he commanded, ſaying, <hi>Obey not thoſe that Rule over you?</hi> or, <hi>Submit not to ſuch Ordinances of Man?</hi> Let them who call for Scripture to atteſt every Ceremony, ſhew where God has therein <hi>forbidden Superiours to command,</hi> or <hi>us to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey</hi> ſuch things? and then there may be ſome tinkling of reaſon, among the the huge <hi>Vox &amp; praeterea nihil,</hi> the mighty noiſe, which only ſerves to amaze the ignorant, and to drown the whiſpers of <hi>Seditious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timations,</hi> and to deter well-meaning ſouls from that <hi>ſubjection,</hi> which Scripture, Reaſon, and Experience teaches to be due to <hi>Superiours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We our ſelves of our own accord do many things for which God hath given us no particular Command: Is it <hi>unlawful</hi> in it ſelf for a Man to ſtand or kneel at his Prayers? certainly no: for if it be, it is becauſe it is againſt ſome Law of Nature, or againſt ſome Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in Gods Word: But it is againſt none of theſe; and therefore it is not unlawful in it ſelf to do them. If therefore it be lawful to do them before they are commanded, certainly it is lawful after; for ſince God has made it our duties to obey the Commands of our Superiours, their Commands cannot make that unlawful, which was lawful before: but if nothing is to be done, but what is commanded in Scripture expreſly in every <hi>particular circumſtance,</hi> we ſhall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52836:10"/> never finde the <hi>true Worſhip of God,</hi> either in <hi>Geneva</hi> or <hi>Scotland</hi> or <hi>Amſterdam</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Therefore the ſumm is this, the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs</hi> of old never ſuffered for diſobedience in <hi>things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God has no where prohibited our obedience in ſuch things, though we ſee no reaſon why they ſhould be commanded: for himſelf has been pleaſed to appoint ſuch things as do not appear to be naturally neceſſary, and likewiſe his ſervants, even under the Goſpel, and he has rewarded ſuch obedience. He has alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded obedience to every ordinance of man. Thoſe things before they were ordinances, were in themſelves lawful, and therefore are ſo after, becauſe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand cannot make them otherwiſe: for he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them is appointed by God to this very end, that he might command, therefore it plainly appears that there is a <hi>neceſſity of Subjection in things indifferent. We muſt needs be ſubject.</hi> But wherein lies the neceſſity? this is the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second thing</hi> which I come now to treat of; how it is neceſſary that we be ſubject in <hi>things indifferent.</hi> And before we weigh thoſe Arguments that prove this, we muſt conſider that it is <hi>impoſſible</hi> to perform the worſhip of God without ſuch things as (before they are commanded) are indifferent.</p>
            <p>The whole World, both Chriſtians, Jews, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens agree upon this, <hi>that God is to be worſhipped;</hi> but at what time, in what place, with what circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances is not generally agreed upon. Whether on the laſt, or firſt day of the week, whether in a private houſe, or in a publick place ſet apart for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; whether ſitting, or ſtanding, or kneeling, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52836:10"/> till the Law of God or man has determined. But at ſome of theſe times, in ſome of theſe places, with ſome of theſe Ceremonies, the Worſhip of God muſt be performed; and there is no man that exclaims againſt a Ceremony, but is his own accuſer, if he ever ſayes his Prayers: for he muſt either uſe the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of ſtanding, or ſitting,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.40.20.36.21.5. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.35.</note> or (if he can ſtoop ſo low) of kneeling, or lying proſtrate; and one of theſe is as much a Ceremony as another: he that ſtands as ſtiff as the Phariſee, is as ceremonious, as he that kneels with the Apoſtle, lies proſtrate like our Saviour: and in ſome of theſe Ceremonies the Worſhip of God muſt be performed: And ſince any of them is as lawful as the other, the Superiour may appoint which he in Reaſon and Conſcience thinks fitting; and in ſo doing he commands nothing <hi>unlawful:</hi> and therefore we muſt be ſubject to either, which he ſhall appoint; and that</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe <hi>God hath ſo commanded;</hi> which queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſs were of it ſelf a ſufficient obligation, though alone. And he that will deny that God hath ſo comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, muſt firſt eraſe many places of Scripture. For God has as plainly therein commanded honour <hi>your Father and Mother,</hi> and <hi>obey thoſe that have the rule over you,</hi> as he hath ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt have none other Gods before me.</hi> Therein alſo is recorded that as dreadful vengeance has been inflicted, upon the diſobedient to earthly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, as upon the rebellious to the King of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Therein alſo he has plainly told us, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7. that <hi>The Prieſts lips ſhould preſerve knowledge,</hi> and that the people <hi>ſhould ſeek the Law at his mouth: for he is the meſſenger of the Lord of Hoſts:</hi> and were not men plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſtinate, as well as prejudiced; they could not but be convinced that the Goſpel gives no liberty, nor
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52836:11"/> makes ſo wide a gap for licentiouſneſs, as to give them power to do what they liſt, either in matters of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual or civil concern:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17.</note> but manifeſtly injoynes us to give <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due, and not only to <hi>Fear God;</hi> but alſo to <hi>Honour the King.</hi> And queſtionleſs Chriſt gave not that great power to his Church, but with an intent they ſhould be obeyed: when he ſaid that <hi>whatſoever</hi> they <hi>ſhould bind on earth ſhould be bound in Heaven:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18.</note> 
               <hi>and whatſoever they ſhould looſe on earth ſhould be looſed in Heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.3.</note> Nay though <hi>Scribes and Phariſees</hi> which are <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> ſit in <hi>Moſes his Chair,</hi> though their lives were not fit for imitation;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 10.16.</note> yet he tells his diſciples their Precepts muſt be obeyed; and <hi>whatſoever they ſay unto them they muſt doe.</hi> And if this be the Word of God: <hi>He that deſpiſeth you deſpiſeth me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13 1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher power. Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man:</hi> and the like. I ſay, if this be the Word of God, and this Word of God has any power over us, <hi>We muſt be ſubject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> God has not onely injoyned this in his written Word, but alſo in thoſe Precepts of Reaſon which he has imprinted by the hand of Nature. For Unity in the external Worſhip of him who is one God, is neceſſary for the well-being of the Church. For commonly, Unity and Peace, like <hi>Hippocrates</hi> his Twins, are born and dye together: for we know there are no greater Hatred and Animoſities in the World, than what have riſen from <hi>Difference</hi> in <hi>Religion.</hi> And as the holy Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 113.1.</note> and Reaſon will inform us, that it is a <hi>Pleaſant thing for Brethren to dwell together in Unity:</hi> ſo ſad experience will tell us, that Diviſion tends to the diſſolution of Concord: and carries men into war and bloodſhed, cruelty and oppreſſion, and no combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52836:11"/> have been more furious and dreadful, than thoſe that have been kindled from Altar ſet up againſt Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar: for what will not men doe, for that Religion that they think is true? and for that Cauſe which they think is Gods? and ſuch an Opinion has every man of his own particular cauſe, and therefore will he hazard Life and Eſtate for promoting it; and all that are not of his way, are as zealous in procuring advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages for theirs. What better expedient therefore can there be to ſurceaſe theſe differences among the Subjects of the <hi>Prince of Peace,</hi> and to unite them in <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Love and Charity, than to preſcribe one mode of Worſhip for all to embrace, which is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Will of that one God whom we all wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? that ſince there is <hi>one Lord, one Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,</hi> we who profeſs this one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, ſhould be alſo of one mind:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10.</note> ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly joyned together according to the Apoſtles injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in the <hi>ſame minde, and in the ſame judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the grand neceſſity of this will further appear, if we conſider how often the Apoſtle inculcates this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing: it is this he begins with, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. which he preſſes with Intreaty, and conjures them by that bleſſed Name to which all ſhould bow and yield. Now, <hi>I beſeech you brethren by the Name of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that ye ſpeak the ſame thing: and that there be no Diviſions among you.</hi> And it is this he ends with 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11. and endears the Command with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of a Bleſſing, which will ſufficiently crown our Obedience, <hi>Be of one mind, live in peace, and the God of peace ſhall be with you:</hi> and wherefore is this Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo frequently repeated? but to ſhew how highly neceſſary Unity is, ſince without it, there will be little
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52836:12"/> of that Peace and Charity which ſhould be among <hi>Chriſtans,</hi> which makes <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>Societies</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſince Unity is the Bond of Peace: Since, unleſs ſome particular way be preſcribed, Men will have ſeveral Modes of Religious worſhip; ſince Governors preſcribe this or that way, for all to embrace, to the end differences and miſchief might be prevented, <hi>We muſt needs be ſubject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Without <hi>ſubjection</hi> there can be no order, but a ſtrange confuſion. If there be no obedience from the Child to the Parent: If there be no ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Servant to the Maſter: No ſubmiſſion from the Subject to the Ruler, it would be ſafer living a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Beaſts of the Wilderneſs, than among men. We are not all born Parents, or Maſters, or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; and queſtionleſs we ought not to uſurp theſe places. For God has commanded Children to obey their Parents, Servants their Maſters, and alſo Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects their Governours. And if a Parent, or Maſter ſhould command his Child, or Servant, in the publick duties of his Family, to uſe this or that Prayer with him, at this or that time, in this or that place, in this or that poſture: What place of Scripture, or what Precept of nature forbids their obedience, ſo it be not contrary to the Word of God? and if a Parent, or Maſter has this power over a Child,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.</note> or Servant; why may not our Superiours appoint the like things to thoſe whom God had committed to their charge, for whom they muſt give an account? why may they not provide that all things be done in <hi>decency</hi> and in <hi>order?</hi> ſince, if there be any undecencies, any diſorders, they muſt be as liable to puniſhment at the great day, as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52836:12"/> any Parent, or Maſter, for the diſorders, and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencies of his Child or Servant. And that Man that diſobeyes his Superiours, at the ſame time teaches, and pleads that his Child or Servant may refuſe obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to himſelf. For he has no other Charter for his liberty. And there is no more ground for the levelling of Kingdoms, than for making all equal in Families: And God hath given us no warrant for either,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14 33.</note> for he is the <hi>God of Order,</hi> not <hi>the Author of Confuſion.</hi> If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we break from thoſe ſtations which his moſt wiſe Providence has ſet us, if with the Complices of <hi>Corah</hi> we take too much upon us, though with <hi>Uzzah</hi> to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that Ark, which <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>Prophaneneſs</hi> has put into a tottering condition, we provoke the God of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and have cauſe to fear his vengeance. <hi>Wherefore we muſt needs be ſubject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> We muſt needs be ſubject, becauſe our <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours muſt needs command.</hi> Men commonly are apt to run into error; and the pride or ignorance of ſome Men, makes them as apt to deceive, and to be deceived: To miſlead, and to be miſled into Factions and Diviſions, and thoſe Diviſions breed a diſlike between this or that party; and that diſlike produces uncharitableneſs; and this uncharitableneſs proceeds to hatred, and this hatred brings forth cruelty, blood, and ruine, to the ſcandal and undoing of Religion, and Juſtice. Now thoſe whom God ſets over a Nation, are bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to prevent theſe miſeries; and to inſtitute ſome ways to reduce Men to that Unity, Love, and Charity, which ſhould be among Chriſtians. If therefore they be bound in Conſcience to command, we no leſs to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey: For without our Obedience, their Commands can be no Remedy. If the Governours of a Church or
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52836:13"/> Nation, do not endeavour to prevent by ſome injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, thoſe miſeries which fall upon a people, for whoſe Souls they watch; they queſtionleſs muſt give an account at the great Audit. And ſo likewiſe they who are the people of ſuch a Church or Nation, if they obey not thoſe that rule over them, in thoſe Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which for ſo good an end are laid upon them, they will find a dreadful doom at the laſt day, when they ſhall appear before his Tribunal, who is the God of Love and Unity. Wherefore <hi>we muſt needs be ſubject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus we ſee in what things we muſt be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            <p>And alſo wherein lies the neceſſity.</p>
            <p>And I preſume this neceſſity is not taken away, by the ſuſpenſion of the penal Laws. And my preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo far from being groundleſs, that it is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the words of the Apoſtle, in that part of my Text which I am now going to treat of. Which tells us; we <hi>muſt be ſubject not only for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake;</hi> not only for fear of the Puniſhment, but alſo for the love of the Duty.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For <hi>Wrath; to avoid this we muſt be ſubject:</hi> For ſelf-preſervation is a duty which cannot be diſpenſed with; and therefore that Man that ſhall ſuffer, rather than perform this or that thing which is indifferent, his blood is upon his own head. He that will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice his Life, or Health, or Eſtate, to an obſtinate groundleſs humour, although he ſcruples a Ceremony, is ſo far Superſtitious, that he is a great Idolater, for he offers up all to his own vain imagination. For what ſhould make kneeling at our Prayers leſs lawful than ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? or a form of Prayer, than a <hi>Directory?</hi> ſince no
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52836:13"/> Scripture commands the latter, rather than the former. One is commanded at leaſt by thoſe whom God hath ſet over us: The other neither by God or Man. And what can better merit the name of <hi>Will-Worſhip,</hi> than that which is ſet up by every particular Man's will?</p>
            <p>But here is the Grand inducement to diſobedience in ſuch things. Men call that <hi>perſecution,</hi> which is but being <hi>buffeted for their faults;</hi> and glory in ſuffering for the Cauſe of God, when alas there is no ſuch thing. For God never required this at their hands: Therefore when we exclude our ſelves from the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Church or Nation wherein we live, rather than obey in ſuch things as are no where proved to be unlawful. When Men have ſuffered their bodies to be impriſoned, their Eſtates to be waſted, and by this means their Families to be unprovided for, to ſuffer Hunger, and Thirſt, and all other kind of Wants: Who has exacted ſuch ſevere things from them? that they ſhould endure theſe juſt effects of the <hi>Superiours wrath, rather than be ſubject?</hi> Has God? if he has, let us know where; Is it not rather the ſecret whiſper of fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? or the Itch of vain-glory, to be counted ſufferers for the ſake of Chriſt? Or, do we pretend it is the Spirit of God within us, that ſtirs us up to this diſobedience, and makes us undergo ſuch hardſhips? If we do, it is but meerly a pretence: For the Spirit of God never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts it ſelf. And the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and other holy Men, ſpake as they were moved by the ſame Holy Ghoſt, that theſe Men pretend to be led by; and they never told us that we ſhould refuſe ſubjection to ſuch Commands, to bring wrath upon our ſelves: But contrariwiſe the Apoſtle tells us, that for this reaſon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52836:14"/> 
               <hi>we muſt be ſubject, that we might avoid the wrath.</hi> But this is removed, at leaſt the effects of it, till the great King of Heaven ſhall <hi>render vengeance to all the Children of diſobedience.</hi> But yet there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains a</p>
            <p>Second Reaſon of our ſubjection to Earthly Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, which ſhall never be removed, till the Earth ſhall be diſſolved, and the Heavens themſelves ſhall paſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. And this alſo is ſet down in my Text, and that is for Conſcience ſake; out of <hi>Conſcience we muſt be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that this may appear, we muſt again review thoſe Arguments which prove obedience neceſſary. For if God has commanded ſubjection; if Reaſon tells us that without it there cannot be Unity, and thoſe bleſſed effects of it, to which we are ſo frequently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted: That without Subjecton there will be no Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but Confuſion; that Men are apt to run into Errours: And that our Superiours muſt needs reſtrain theſe inclinations. If things be thus, and thus, as by the premiſed Reaſons has been proved; then queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, <hi>we are bound in Conſcience to be ſubject.</hi> Nay, if not only the Penalties were ſuſpended, but even the Commands themſelves were ſo relaxed, that every Man might worſhip God as he pleaſed; nay, might chooſe whether he would worſhip him or no: Yet Juſtice obliges him to worſhip him, &amp; Reaſon requires that this Worſhip be performed in Unity. And it cannot but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear evident to any that have not wholly diſclaimed Reaſon, that ſhould there be ſuch a liberty granted, that every Man might worſhip God as he pleaſed, Men would ſee ſuch monſtrous iſſues from thence, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and diſtractions, ſuch a confuſion and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52836:14"/> and from thence ſuch debate, and envy, and hatred, that all <hi>ſober good men of what perſwaſion ſoever,</hi> would deſire to have <hi>ſome bounds preſcrib'd them,</hi> to keep the <hi>Chriſtian World</hi> in peace, and to limit the <hi>extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> of Men. So plainly would they ſee that <hi>We muſt needs be ſubject,</hi> even <hi>for Conſcience-ſake.</hi> But the God of Peace and Unity, grant us Wiſdom at a cheaper rate, and that we may never learn it again by ſo ſad experience.</p>
            <p>And if we would ſee what manner of poſture things would be in, if there were no Order appointed in the Worſhip of God, we need not travel far for information: we may read enough of it in the ſad acts of our late Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical times, to cauſe Horrour and Conſternation in the minds all good Men. Something may be ſeen in the ruines of the Houſes of God in the Land, whoſe rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh are ſad Monuments of unbridled Zeal. Sacriledge, and Cruelty, and Rapine may be glutted, if they look back into thoſe days, when there was no King, or at leaſt no King obeyed in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and every man did that which right in his own Eyes. When there were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as many Modes of Religion as Men, and theſe as variable as the Moon; nay, as the inconſtant hours of <hi>Autumn.</hi> Yet every one at all times pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to be in the right, and all the reſt in the wrong. So that no Man knew who to truſt to, or what to hold to. That all this tended to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Peace, to the ruine of Humane Society, and to the unſetling of all things. He that was of one Religion to day, to morrow would be of another, and the next of a third, and at laſt of none at all. As we have ſeen ſome, who have forſaken the Center, and got into the Round; and turned from <hi>Presbytery,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:52836:15"/> to <hi>Independency,</hi> from this to <hi>Anabaptiſm,</hi> from this to <hi>Browniſm,</hi> and from this to <hi>Quakeriſm,</hi> and ſo toſt about with every wind of Doctrine, till at laſt, by the juſt Judgment of God, they have been thrown quite beſides all <hi>Religion to God</hi> or <hi>Honeſty to man;</hi> one day denying the dues of the Church, the next all other whatſoever: for they who at firſt denyed the Revenues of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, at laſt proceeded to Opinions, that all things ſhould be common; and ſometimes even to the very practice of Levelling; teaching that onely the <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhould inherit</hi> the Earth, and all other to be rooted out from the land of the living: and themſelves (though parties chiefly concern'd) were Judges and Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in the caſe. But I deſire that no other uſe might be made of theſe ſad Memoires, than to move us to pity, and to pray for thoſe that have been guilty of the ſins of Diſobedience and Schiſm, that they may repent of them, and we may diſcover what Deſolation theſe Sins have wrought in the Earth; that ſeeing what miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs and fatal miſeries have proceeded thence, we may be convinced that we are bound <hi>in Conſcience to be ſubject,</hi> to prevent ſuch ruine, as we may otherwiſe bring upon our ſelves and others.</p>
            <p>And thus we ſee in what things we <hi>muſt be ſubject.</hi> In thoſe things which God has commanded; and in thoſe things which he has not forbidden: for we have neither precept nor example to the contrary. No place in the whole Scripture forbids us to obey our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, neither did ever any of the Martyrs ſuffer for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience in ſuch things.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we have alſo ſeen the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in ſuch things. 1. Becauſe God has ſo command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. 2. Becauſe Reaſon alſo requires it: becauſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52836:15"/> peace is neceſſary, and this cannot be had without Unity: nor will there be Unity without Obedience to thoſe that appoint us the wayes we ſhould obſerve. 3. Becauſe without it there will be no order. 4. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is a neceſſity that the Superiour muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We have alſo ſeen the Apoſtles reaſons why we muſt be ſubject. 1. For wrath; rather ſubmit in ſuch things as God hath not forbidden than incurr the puniſhment. 2. Though no puniſhment be threatned for Diſobedience, yet, even for Conſcience ſake we ought to be ſubject, rather than bring ſuch miſeries upon our ſelves and others, as are the ſad conſequence of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience.</p>
            <p>But to conclude all; The Providence of the Almighty has plac'd us, where there is nothing commanded us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Will: there is not a Circumſtance in our Worſhip, not an expreſſion in our LITURGY that God has any where <hi>forbidden:</hi> and therefore queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we ought to be ſubject, for God has commanded us ſo to be: and if his Word had been ſilent herein, yet Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the practice of all Nations has ſpoken loud enough in the Caſe: becauſe <hi>No Worſhip can be without ſome Ceremonies; No Peace, Order or Decency, without Unity in thoſe Ceremonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore,</hi> although it has pleaſed our <hi>Superiours</hi> to ſuſpend the Puniſhment due to Diſobedience, yet the taking away the Penalty, takes away neither the <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> nor <hi>convenience</hi> of the <hi>Command,</hi> nor the neceſſity of our Obedience to it, if we think we muſt be ſubject <hi>for Conſcience ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If, therefore, we have any regard to the expreſs Commands of God's Vicegerent, who ſtill injoynes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52836:16"/> Obedience, though not upon any penalty; if we have any reſpect to the Will of God himſelf, who has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us alſo for Conſcience ſake to ſubmit; if we have any love to Order, to Unity, and Peace, <hi>we muſt needs be ſubject;</hi> if we would not have the moſt pure Church in the World rent in pieces; if we would not have that Religion deſtroyed, which ſo ſtrictly injoynes <hi>Obedience to God,</hi> Juſtice, and Love, and Charity to <hi>Man, we muſt be ſubject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is one thing (though not the onely thing) which has given occaſion to ſome undiſcerning or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable perſons to <hi>refuſe Subjection:</hi> and that is the wicked lives of ſome, who pretend to belong to our <hi>Church:</hi> But let us endeavour to have our <hi>Converſations</hi> as unblamable as her <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> that the malice of the Adverſary may yet have leſs cauſe to object, and the unwary may not have this for an Argument, <hi>Your lives are bad, therefore your Religion is naught.</hi> And let ſuch as make this an occaſion of their Separation, be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to conſider, That they ought not to perſecute that Religion with <hi>Schiſm,</hi> which others have ſmitten with <hi>profaneneſs:</hi> for the Religion may be good, though the Profeſſors of it be bad: and that Chriſts Religion was never the worſe, becauſe one of his Apoſtles had a Devil.</p>
            <p>And let us be entreated by the words of Saint <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>If there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of Love, if any fellowſhip of the Spirit, to fulfill</hi> the <hi>joy</hi> of all, good men, <hi>that we be like minded, having the ſame love being of one accord and of one mind.</hi> And that we may be ſo, the ſame Apoſtle gives a very fit expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and intreats us to uſe it, Rom. 16.17. <hi>Now I
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52836:16"/> beſeech you brethren, mark thoſe that cauſe diviſion, and offences, contrary to the doctrine you have received, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void them:</hi> not out of curioſity frequenting the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of thoſe that divide from us; leſt God puniſh our Curioſity, by giving us up to be enſnared by their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</p>
            <p>And let us ſubmit to the ſupream King of Heaven, and to the great Biſhop of our Souls, and to the Powers upon Earth for his ſake: that at the laſt day, when he ſhall ſummon us all to appear before his dreadful Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, we may be received, where we ſhall enjoy eternal <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Unity,</hi> and <hi>Uniformity,</hi> together with Angels, and Saints, who have obeyed him in this, and all other his Commands, and have been <hi>ſubject not only for wrath, but alſo for conſcience ſake.</hi> To which bleſſed Society, may he in his good time conduct us, who is the God of peace, to whom, together with the Son, and Holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed, as is moſt due, all Praiſe, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Adoration, hence forth and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
